A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services, Series H FA317
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services, Series H
1886-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine)
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
Spelman family
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
China Medical Board (U.S)
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Spelman Fund
Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial
Rockefeller, John D.
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Rockefeller, David
International Education Board
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Rockefeller Foundation
Rockefeller University
Sealantic Fund, New York
General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.)
Standard Oil Company
Rockefeller family
Rockefeller, Winthrop
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Davison Fund
FA317
186 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research except where particular restrictions are noted.
Material in the Rockefeller family collections which provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net worth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; C Business Interests; D Civic Interests; E Cultural Interests; F Economic Reform Interests; G Educational Interests; H Friends and Services; I Homes; J Housing Interests; K Medical Interests; L Real Estate; M Maps and Memorabilia; N Religious Interests; O Rockefeller Boards; P Welfare - General Files; Q World Affairs; R Welfare - Youth Files; S Documents; T Public Relations; U Public Land Law Review Commission; V Greenrock; W Properties; X Costume Collection; Y Media; Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal; AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller; AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in twenty sections, as follows:
Biography; Cemeteries; Chandler and Rudd; Clubs; Dancing; Detectives; Doctors; Donations; Friends and Relations; Horses, Stables, Garages; Office; Portraits; Publicity; Taxes; Requests for Photos of Art Objects; Washington Appeals; Form Letters; Foreign Mail; Family of Alta Rockefeller Prentice; Miscellaneous.
Scope and Contents note
The Friends and Services series is primarily John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s personal correspondence with his friends and relations. Other files deal with a variety of support, service, and administrative activities such as the operation of the Family Office, family membership in social clubs, family doctors, management of family garages and stables, and arrangement for the biographies of John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
The series contains correspondence between members of the Rockefeller family and the Family Office and friends, relatives, employees, and associates. The correspondence deals with a wide variety of topics. The family members who figure most prominently in the papers are John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Martha Baird Rockefeller, Edith Rockefeller McCormick and members of her family, and Alta Rockefeller Prentice and members of her family.
There are twenty sections within the Friends and Services series. Each section is described individually here.
The Biography section covers the years 1894-1960. Materials in this section discuss the selection of an author and other arrangements for biographies of John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
The Cemeteries section spans the years 1879-1954 and discusses the purchase of burial plots and the upkeep of grave sites.
The Chandler & Rudd section covers the years 1902-1958. Chandler & Rudd were grocers; W. C. Rudd was John D. Rockefeller, Sr.'s brother-in-law. Topics covered in this section of the Friends and Services series include family loans to the firm.
The Clubs section, with documents dating from 1910 to 1961, includes materials on the family's memberships in and their support of social clubs.
The Dancing section covers the years 1914-1952; documents in this section include invitations received to dances and arrangements for orchestras for dances at 10 West 54th Street.
The Detectives section spans the years 1914-1940. Items in this section include requests for positions as private detectives, information about detectives hired to investigate impersonation of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and John D. Rockefeller 3rd (2 cases), and extortion letters (2 cases).
The Doctors section covers the years 1905-1960. This section consists of files on individual family physicians, mostly correspondence reflecting friendship between John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and family doctors. It also includes information on gifts of appreciation from John D. Rockefeller, Jr., some medical records on John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and the brothers as boys, and some bills. The entire Doctors section is closed to research.
The Donations section dates from 1894 to 1961 and includes information about small John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. donations and gifts of money, mostly to individuals.
The Friends and Relations section, which spans the years 1886-1961, is primarily composed of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s correspondence with a multitude of friends, associates, relatives, and acquaintances.
The Horses, Stables, and Garages section covers the years 1914-1961. Information in this section details the construction, management, and disposal of New York City garages, and the purchase of horses and automobiles.
The Office section, dated 1919-1961, contains information on the management of the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller. Also included in this section are some employee pension files.
The Portraits section, which spans the years 1904-1962, discusses the arrangements for portraits of 1st, 2nd, and 3rd generations.
The Publicity section dates from 1907 to 1961. Materials in this section include clipped articles, correspondence with a variety of magazines and publishing companies regarding requests for interviews, financial assistance, and appreciation for friendly editorials.
The Taxes section covers the years 1886-1961 and consists of information on real estate and income tax records for John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr., appeals from and contributions to tax reform organizations, and payment of federal and state unemployment tax for family employees.
The Requests for Photos of Art Objects section consists of one folder and discusses Martha Baird Rockefeller's policy against allowing photographs of her art objects to be used publicly.
The Washington Appeals section, dated from 1944-1961, contains information about small gifts made to private Washington, DC organizations.
The Form Letters section, consisting of one folder, contains samples of commonly written letters and legal documents in the Family Office.
The Foreign Mail section spans the years 1907-1961 and contains financial appeals from foreign organizations and individuals.
The Family of Alta Rockefeller Prentice section, dated from 1901-1961, pertains to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s sister, the management of her and her heirs' financial affairs by John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr., and the establishment and maintenance of trusts for members of the Prentice family.
The final section of this series, the Miscellaneous File, contains "a truly kaleidoscopic potpourri of odds and ends."
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Medical education; Medical research; Maternal health services; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Medical care; New York (State); Parks -- New York (State); Medical sciences; New York (N.Y.); Performing arts; Prohibition; Public health; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; Public policy; Public health administration; Urban policy; Urban renewal; World War I; World War II; Public welfare; Religion; Religious institutions; Restoration and conservation; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Travel; United States; Government policy; Folk art; Federal government -- United States; Family planning; Public relations; Housing rehabilitation; Health insurance; Philanthropy -- United States; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Economic development; Art; Art, Modern; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Education -- United States; Education; Economics; Economic policy; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charitable contributions; Charities -- Investments; Charities; Philanthropy; Business; Arts; Capital investments; Business enterprises, Foreign; International relations; International education; Juvenile delinquency; International relations -- United States; Civic improvement; Child welfare; International economic relations; International cooperation; Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Spelman family; Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman; China Medical Board (U.S); Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Center; Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth); Spelman Fund; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Rockefeller, John D.; Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Rockefeller, David; International Education Board; Mauze, Abby Rockefeller; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller University; Sealantic Fund, New York; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Standard Oil Company; Rockefeller family; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Rockefeller, Winthrop; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); Davison Fund
- Biography
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Doubleday, 1908; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Frank Doubleday assigned to write John D. Rockefeller's biography; interviews; Starr J. Murphy checked manuscript. Preparation of "Reminiscences;" John D. Rockefeller corrections; publication. Oil men's comments on "Reminiscences;" publication in book form; royalties. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates, Frank Doubleday.
    File Plan note
    39
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Doubleday, 1908-1914; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - General, 1916-1932; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Ivy Lee suggests employment of journalist to collect facts about John D. Rockefeller; idea approved in 1916 - W. O. Inglis employed. Comments on other biographers - Englebrecht, Flynn, Nevins, Winkleman.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - General, 1933-1943; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Ivy Lee suggests employment of journalist to collect facts about John D. Rockefeller.; idea approved in 1916 - W. O. Inglis employed. Comments on other biographers - Englebrecht, Flynn, Nevins, Winkleman.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - General, 1938; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 0004A)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - W. H. Allen, 1927-1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Rockefeller, Giant, Dwarf and Symbol"; John D. Rockefeller reaction to manuscript. Publication; reviews.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - F. N. Doubleday, 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sale of "Reminiscences."
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - R. W. Smith, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Unauthorized biography. Library of Congress check sheet of Rockefeller references.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - W. T. Taylor, 1918-1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Engaged to check facts on Standard Oil Co.; John D. Rockefeller comment on finished work, 1923; Nevins used manuscript.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Biographical Sketch, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Revision of standard biography by Ivy Lee.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Taylor Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Typed copy of Taylor's study of Standard Oil used by Nevins. Correspondents include Walter F. Taylor.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Articles and Correspondence, 1894-1908 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    1894, Frederick T. Gates proposed biography for New York Tribune volume; Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates and John D. Rockefeller comments on newspaper articles. 1907 Starr J. Murphy letters regarding changing opinion of John D. Rockefeller. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Frederick T. Gates.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Articles and Correspondence - Cleveland Plain Dealer, 1905-1906 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Interview in which John D. Rockefeller was misquoted regarding French people; corrected in New York Papers; favorable staff reaction to article.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Newspaper Articles, 1906-1911 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Interviews with John D. Rockefeller; stories about him - some factual.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - W. O. Inglis, 1916-1921; Folder 1 of 5 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Ivy Lee introduction of Inglis to John D. Rockefeller via golf; Inglis hired, 1917, to collect information on John D. Rockefeller; preparation of short sketches. Inglis' ideas regarding biography. Sources of information; comments on work by Tarbell, A. Brisbane, G. E. Vincent, etc. Decision to limit publication of work; personal problems. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gifts to Inglis; Inglis work for Nelson A. Rockefeller. Death. Correspondents include Ivy Lee, John D. Rockefeller, W. O. Inglis, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - W. O. Inglis, 1921-1923; Folder 2 of 5 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - W. O. Inglis, 1924-1932; Folder 3 of 5 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - W. O. Inglis, 1915-1931; Folder 4 of 5 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - W. O. Inglis, 1932-1949; Folder 5 of 5 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - W. O. Inglis, 1940; Folder 5 of 5 (Box 3, Folder 0018A)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis Controversy, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Inglis desire to publish book on work with Nelson A. Rockefeller's Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (CIAA) during War; decision against publication; conferences with Inglis. Correspondents include W. O. Inglis, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John E. Lockwood.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Notes on Conversations with John D. Rockefeller - Book 1, 1917-1918 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    One set of 5 volumes on white paper; one set of carbons on yellow paper - 5 volumes. Index prepared by Inglis for carbon set.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Notes on Conversations with John D. Rockefeller - Book 2, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Notes on Conversations with John D. Rockefeller - Book 3 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Notes on Conversations with John D. Rockefeller - Book 4 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Notes on Conversations with John D. Rockefeller - Book 5 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 1, 1920-1924; Folder 1 of 12 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    Four drafts of biography - final draft used by Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1928.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 1, 1920-1924; Folder 2 of 12 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 1, 1920-1924; Folder 3 of 12 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 2, 1920-1924; Folder 4 of 12 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 2, 1920-1924; Folder 5 of 12 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 2, 1920-1924; Folder 6 of 12 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 3, 1920-1924; Folder 7 of 12 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 3, 1920-1924; Folder 8 of 12 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 3, 1920-1924; Folder 9 of 12 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 4, 1920-1924; Folder 10 of 12 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 4, 1920-1924; Folder 11 of 12 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Narrative Biography - Draft 4, 1920-1924; Folder 12 of 12 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Notes on Interview - Impressions, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    John D. Rockefeller regarding Standard Oil, John D. Rockefeller regarding Youth, War, Religion, Character, Philanthropy, Notes on John D. Rockefeller's youth and family, notes on Standard Oil and oil industry, Tarbell & Floyd.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Notes - General, 1907-1920 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    Miscellaneous notes on rebates. Mesopotamia oil fields.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Notes - Mr. Rockefeller, Sr. vs. Tarbell, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 39)
    John D. Rockefeller comments on Tarbell's history of Standard Oil.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Notes - Magazine Articles - McClures, Ida Tarbell, 1905 (Box 9, Folder 40)
    John D. Rockefeller comments on Tarbell, McClures, 1905 article.
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Newspaper Clippings - General, pre 1900; Folder 1 of 6 (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Newspaper Clippings - General, 1905-1927; Folder 2 of 6 (Box 9, Folder 0041A)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Newspaper Clippings - General, 1911-1919; Folder 3 of 6 (Box 9, Folder 42)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Newspaper Clippings - General, 1920-1922; Folder 4 of 6 (Box 9, Folder 0042A)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Newspaper Clippings - General, 1923-1929; Folder 5 of 6 (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Inglis - Newspaper Clippings - General, 1930-1934; Folder 6 of 6 (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Newspaper Clippings - Unspecified, 1935-1939; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Newspaper Clippings - Unspecified, 1940-1949; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Biography - John D. Rockefeller - Newspaper Clippings - Unspecified, 1950-1959; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 10, Folder 47)